Finding Aid for Thomas R. Stockton papers, 1917-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas R. Stockton papers 1917-2013, 1950s-1990s
Stockton, Thomas R.
7.3 linear feet including oversize
2013118 Aa 2
Thomas Stockton (1921-2012) was the manager of Ford Powertrain and Driveline Research at Ford Motor Company. This collection features many of his work papers and diagrams mainly relating to turbine and rotary engine research during his time at Ford, more general Ford documents (ex. Service manuals, project plans, in-company communications, etc.), his various patents and invention disclosures, as well as documents and photographs relating to his time as an officer of the Early Engines Club and a member of the North American Model Engineering Society.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Charles Stockton (Donor no. 10968 ) in August 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas Stockton was born July 6, 1921 in Cincinnati, Ohio to Bertha (Gantvoort) Stockton and Eric Stockton. He received a Bachelor of Science degree from Purdue University (1942) and a Master of Science degree from the University of Michigan (1950), both for the study of Mechanical Engineering. He served briefly in the United States Army (1946). He married Barbara (Johnston) Stockton in 1952, with whom he had five children. His career was spent mostly at Ford Motor Company (1950-1987), where he worked on automatic transmission and gas turbine design, receiving numerous patents (approx. 65). Before his employment at Ford Motor Company, Stockton worked with the Wright Aeronautical Corp. as a Liaison Engineer on Wright R-2600 and R-3350 aircraft engines (1943-1945), Kett Tool Co. as a Design/Development Engineer on small electric power tools (1945-1946), and Procter & Gamble as a Design/Development Engineer on food processing machinery (1947-1949). After his retirement from Ford in 1987, he became a free-lance engineering consultant, continuing his work relationship with Ford including within the Ford Alpha division (1993-1995) and FFD-USA (1995-1996), as well as working with many other engineering companies (GKN, Advanced Power Technology, Henry Ford Museum Adult Education Program, etc.).
Outside of his work as the manager of Powertrain and Driveline Research at Ford, Stockton was very active as a member of the Early Engine Club, an organization which he helped to found, which was focused on the history of antique steam engines. He also taught a popular course on Steam power for the North American Model Engineering Society. Stockton died July 10, 2012 at the age of 91.
Thomas Stockton (1921-2012) was the manager of Ford Powertrain and Driveline Research at Ford Motor Company for 37 years. The papers within this collection focus primarily on different aspects of Stockton's work career with Ford Motor Company but also contain information on Stockton's involvement within different engineering organizations. The collection is divided into six series: the Early Engine Club series, the North American Model Engineering Society series, the Ford Motor Company series, the Research series, the Patents and Invention Disclosures series, and the Retirement and Consultation series. The collection also contains an Outsize box with materials from different series, marked as such within this finding aid.
Subjects:
Stockton, Thomas R.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan.; Automobiles--Design and construction.; Engineers--Michigan.; Engines--Design and construction.; Ford Motor Company.; Turbines--Design and construction.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Slides (photographs)
- Early Engine Club
  The Early Engine Club series (0.3 linear feet, 1952-2009) contains various papers from Stockton's time working with this organization. Among items of interest within this collection are a photo album with various pictures of steam engines and Early Engine Club activities, photographs of the "Arbor Queen" (a steam-powered boat that the club built), newsletters, membership and leadership information, and meeting minutes. Some photographs from this series are located in outsize Box 8.
  - Arbor Queen 2008 (Box 1)
  - Domino's train track designs and correspondence 1997 (Box 1)
  - Early Engine Club papers 1964-2009, undated (Box 1)
    (scattered)
  - The Gas Engine Magazine 1966 (Box 1)
  - Photo album 1969-1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs undated (Box 8)
    (outsize)
  - Photographs and slides 1952-1997, undated (Box 1)
- North American Model Engineering Society
  The North American Model Engineering Society series (0.4 linear feet, 1990-2007) contains an instructional paper on heat engine basics, the original text and figures for Stockton's course on the Study of Steam Power, as well as the finished copy of this course, as well as various papers related to the North American Model Engineering Society.
  - Heat Engine Basics undated (Box 1)
  - North American Model Engineering Society papers 1990-2013 (Box 1)
  - The Study of Steam Power final 2007 (Box 1)
  - The Study of Steam Power original 1992 (Box 1)
  - The Study of Steam Power original figures undated (Box 1)
- Ford Motor Company
  The Ford Motor Company series (0.1 linear feet, 1917-1993) contains various papers from the Ford Motor Company including diagrams and information on the Fordson tractor, promotional programs on various vehicles, photographs from throughout Stockton's time at Ford, and a collection of newspapers, including those from Henry Ford's death in 1947 which are of note.
  - Ford Motor Company papers 1917-1993 (Box 1)
  - Newspapers on Ford's death 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Photographs undated (Box 1)
  - Promotional programs 1956-1960, undated (Box 1)
    (with gaps)
- Research, 1950s-2005
  The Research series (3 linear feet, 1950s-2005) is the largest series within the collection. This series contains Stockton's sketches and designs, calculations, and project analyses on the various research projects (mostly on new engine technologies) that he was involved in throughout his career at Ford Motor Company as well as some research conducted after his retirement. Outsize: Transparencies for the Convertor Controlled Accessory Drive are located within Box 8.
  - Automatic transmission 1950s (Box 1)
  - Converter controlled accessory drive 1995 (Box 1)
  - Flywheel alternator 1994 (Box 1)
  - Front wheel drive gas turbine-model 500 F 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Front wheel drive 4 speed phase II 1966 (Box 1)
  - New turbine power by Ford undated (Box 1)
  - Owner's and operator's manuals
    - Ford gas turbine engine undated (Box 1)
    - Ford gas turbine generator set 1973 (Box 1)
  - R5 radial engine 2005 (Box 1)
  - Torque converter undated (Box 1)
  - Transverse concentric powertrain for a sub-compact front wheel drive car 1967 (Box 1)
  - Body/Chassis Service Manual (Aerostar, Ranger, Explorer) 1993 (Box 2)
  - CD4E automatic transaxle 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Ford gas turbine engine basic training course undated (Box 2)
  - Marketing EngiNEWS 1987 (Box 2)
  - Research correspondence 1991 (Box 2)
  - Consulting projects 1987 (Box 2)
  - Alternator overrunning clutch drive 1993 (Box 3)
  - Converter controlled accessory drive study 1995 (Box 3)
  - Flywheel alternator 1995 (Box 3)
  - Luxury select design (LSD) vehicle 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1991-1994, undated (Box 3)
  - Service manual (Taurus/Sable) 1993 (Box 3)
  - Alternator pulley with roller clutch 1994 (Box 4)
  - Carot powertrain system review 1993 (Box 4)
  - Converter controlled accessory drive 1995 (Box 4)
  - Converter controlled accessory drive transparencies 1995 (Box 8)
  - Design of a two speed automatic transaxle for an electric vehicle 1985 (Box 4)
  - Dual mode continuously variable transmission 1981-1984 (Box 4)
  - Engine papers 1966-1973, undated (Box 4)
  - Flywheel alternator 1994 (Box 4)
  - Flywheel alternator 1995 (Box 4)
  - Ford variable speed accessory drive 1995 (Box 4)
  - Fuel economy of continuously variable transmission 1998 (Box 4)
  - Hybrid technology 1991-2005, undated (Box 4)
  - Model radial aircraft engine 1983 (Box 4)
  - Two speed alternator 1995-1995 (Box 4)
  - Two stage oil pump 1991 (Box 4)
  - Wankel Freon air conditioning compressor 1974 (Box 4)
  - What became of the automotive gas turbine? undated (Box 4)
- Patents and Invention Disclosures 1956-1995
  The Patents and Invention Disclosures series (2.5 linear feet, 1956-1995) contains all of Stockton's patents and invention disclosures (as well as some patents of others that Stockton consulted in producing his own) from throughout his career. Folders within this series are grouped by date rather than by invention, with respect to Stockton's original order in grouping this series.
  - Invention disclosure record 1956-1983 (Box 4)
  - List of patents 1961-1978 (Box 4)
  - 1957-1966, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1962-1967, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1962-1967, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1963-1970, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - 1967-1976, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1973-1978, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1966-1984, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - 1970-1988, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Retirement and Consultation 1957-1996
  The Retirement and Consultation series (1 linear foot, 1957-1996) contains Stockton's consultation correspondence, research for consultation projects, photographs from after his retirement, as well as papers from his retirement and his own personal history record (first draft from 1957 and second from 1996), and certificates that he was awarded after his retirement. A poem written for Stockton on his retirement about his life as an engineer is located in the Box 8 (outsize).
  - Advanced Power Technology 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - Ford Motor Company
    - 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - 1991 (Box 7)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 7)
  - GKN Automotive Components, Inc. 1987-1989 (Box 7)
  - The Gnome Aero Engine undated (Box 7)
  - OMC-Lincoln 1988 (Box 7)
  - Personal history record and miscellaneous 1957-1996 (Box 7)
  - Photographs 1965-1991, undated (Box 7)
  - Retirement card and flyer 1987 (Box 7)
  - Retirement poem undated (Box 8)